New York State Society for Clinical Social Work, Inc.; Records apap290
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Society for Clinical Social Work Records
1965-2021
Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap290
7.4 cubic ft.
Established in 1968 to assist clinical social workers in performing their duties, the New York State Society for Clinical Social Work (NYSSCSW) offers professional support to its members in the practice of clinical psychotherapy. The collection documents the founding, administration, and activities of the NYSSCSW and its various local chapters.
Collection X
Conditions Governing Access
Acquisition Information
The first set of records in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2006. In November 2021, Marsha Wineburgh donated 14 additional boxes of material.
Historical Note
Contained is material concerning the New York State Society for Clinical Social Work (NYSSCSW), an organization founded in 1968 to address growing needs for professional support for private practitioners and to assist in navigating insurance reimbursement issues. Emerging at the same time as a number of other state clinical societies, the NYSSCSW is one of the founding charters of the National Federation of Societies for Clinical Social Work, which in 1971 united the New York chapters with counterparts from Louisiana, California, and Illinois under a shared mission of national advocacy, interstate communication, and the passing of licensing and insurance reimbursement legislation in all 50 states.
The legislative achievements of the Society include the defeat of legislation that would require the supervision of clinical social workers by a psychologist or psychiatrist, the passage of a bill in 1977 that would allow for the reimbursement of clinical social workers by insurance companies who covered other mental health services at the request of the client – the so called "P" law - and a further amendment to that legislation in 1984 which made the equal reimbursement of clinical social workers mandatory for any insurance plan that covered mental health services – the so called "R" law. 2002 saw the accomplishment of the Society's greatest effort yet with the passage of a formal licensure system for clinical social workers in New York. Since then, the NYSSCSW has continued to represent the interests of mental health practitioners in all levels of government, offering education and support to clinical social workers throughout the state.
In addition to advocating for clinical social workers through legislative efforts, the Society also conducts annual education conferences to instruct colleagues on the newest methods for the practice as well as publishing a biannual newsletter, The Clinician.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the New York State Society for Clinical Social Work newsletter, legislative files, material documenting lobbying activity, administrative records, and subject files including a amount of material about programming and events.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into four series all organized chronologically. The first series contains administrative records pertaining to the organization. The second series contains legislation and various lobbying efforts conducted on behalf of the Society. The third series contains publications from the Society and its various local chapters, and the fourth contains materials from events organized by the Society and local chapters as well as information for members regarding the navigation of managed care.
Medicine and Health Care; Social Work; Digital Files
- Administrative Records, 1977-2019; Undated; 1; 1.4 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains files from the tenure of the Society's former presidents Marsha Wineburgh (1980-1981, 2012-2015), Hillel Bodek (2004-2007), and David Phillips (1992-1993); meeting minutes from the New York State Board for Social Work; documents concerning the incorporation of the society and its bylaws; and materials from the New York Board of Regents Professional Practice Committee.
  - Marsha Wineburgh, 1977; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NYSSCSW Information, 1977; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - David Phillips, 1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Code of Ethics, 1981; 2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hillel Bodek, 1982-1987; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - HMO Conference, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barbara Patton, 1990; 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 1992 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - State Board for Social Work, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Organizational Administration, 1993; 2004; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - State Board for Social Work, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 1995 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 1997 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Marsha Wineburgh, 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 1998 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 1999 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Regents Committee on Professional Practice, 1999 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2000 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2001 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2002 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - State Board for Social Work, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Commissioner of Education Regulations, 2004 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board of Regents Rules, 2005 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Office of the Professions - Social Work Guide to Practice, 2005 September (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - State Board for Social Work, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - State Board for Mental Health Practitioners Meeting, 2006 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - State Board for Social Work, 2006 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2007 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2007 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2008 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2008 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2009 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2010 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2010 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - State Board for Mental Health Practitioners Meeting, 2010 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Board of Regents Draft Report, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Board of Regents Professional Practice Committee, 2010; Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Creditentialing of Substance Abuse Counselors, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2011 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2011 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2012 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2012 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2012 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2013 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2013 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2014 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2015 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2016 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2016 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2016 November 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2017 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2017 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2017 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2018 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - State Board for Social Work Meeting, 2019 March 27 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Legislation, 1965-2021; Undated; 2; 4 cubic ft.
  This series contains legislative reports, drafts, and lobbying efforts conducted on behalf of the NYSSCSW throughout its history. Much of the collection concerns the campaigns to establish the "P" and "R" laws as well as the society's efforts to establish a formal license for clinical social workers. Materials from the society's legislative efforts regarding mental health practitioners are also included.
  - Licensing, 1965; 1974-1975; 1977-1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "R" Law, 1970; 1978-1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "P" Law - Optional Insurance, 1974-1977; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medicaid Direct Billing (1 of 2), 1978-1980; 1983; 1987-1989; 2003-2004; 2019 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medicaid Direct Billing (2 of 2), 1978-1980; 1983; 1987-1989; 2003-2004; 2019 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Federal Medicare Law, 1980-1981; 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Confidentiality Legislation, 1980-1982; 1984-1985; 1987-1989; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Regulations for Other Mental Health Professions, 1980-1982; 1984-1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "P" and "R" Legislative Committee Meeting, 1980-1995; 1997; 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "R" Law, 1981 January-1981 February; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "R" Law, 1981 March-1981 December; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "R" Law, 1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jury Duty Exemption, 1982-1984; 1987-1989; 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "R" Law, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "R" Law, 1984 January-1984 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "R" Law, 1984 July-1984 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Psychotherapy Licensing, 1984-1985; 2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "R" Law Celebration and Integration, 1984-1989; 1991; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Psychiatric Examiners Legislation, 1985; 1989-1991; 1993; 2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Siegel Omnibus Bills, 1986; 1993; 1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "R" Law Amendments, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Other Professions Seeking Licensing in New York, 1987; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Workers' Compensation Legislation, 1987-1988; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Licensing, 1988-1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Regulations for Other Mental Health Professions, 1990; 1992; 1995-1997; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Licensing, 1991-1992; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Federal Court Decisions, 1991-1992; 1995-1996; 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York Court Decisions, 1992; 1994; 2003; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Licensing, 1993; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Licensing, 1994; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Licensing, 1995; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Additional Social Work Legislation, 1996; 1998-1999; 2002-2003; 2012; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Licensing, 1996; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Licensing, 1997 January-1997 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Licensing, 1997 August-1997 December (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Continuing Education, 1997; 2006; 2013-2015; Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mandatory Child Abuse Reporting, 1997-1999; 2001; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Multidiscipline Corporate Structure, 1998; 2013; 2015; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Licensing, 1998; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Licensing, 1999 January-1999 May; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bill S.2990, 1999 February (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Licensing, 1999 June-1999 December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Licensing, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Licensing, 2001 January-2001 May; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Licensing, 2001 June-2001 December (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Regulations for Other Mental Health Professions, 2001; 2003-2004; 2009; 2014; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Licensing, 2002 January-2002 March (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Licensing, 2002 April-2002 June (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Licensing, 2002 July-2002 December; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Licensing, 2003 January-2003 March; Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Licensing, 2003 April-2003 May (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Licensing, 2003 June-2003 December; Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Timothy's Law, 2003-2004; 2006; 2008 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Licensing, 2004 January-2004 May; Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Licensing, 2004 June-2004 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Requirements for Mental Health Practitioners, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Licensing, 2005; Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Licensing, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Licensing, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Licensing, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Licensing, 2009; Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Legislation, 2010 January-2010 May; Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Legislation, 2010 June-2010 December; Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Legislation, 2011; Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Conversion Therapy Prohibition, 2012; 2014 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Legislation, 2012; Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Legislation, 2013; Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Out-of-Network Benefits, 2013-2014; Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - SAFE Act, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Legislation, 2014; Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Telehealth, 2014-2015 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Legislation, 2015; Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Legislative Efforts, 2016; Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Legislative Efforts, 2017; Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Legislative Efforts, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Efforts, 2019 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Legislative Report, 2020 January 25 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - School Mental Health Practitioners Bill, 2021 April 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Publications, 1974-2020; Undated; 3; 17 Digital Files; 1 cubic ft.
  This series contains copies of the society's newsletter – later known as "The Clinician" – dating back to 1974, as well as publications circulated by local chapters. The NYSSCSW newsletters often contain a President's Message, ACE Foundation News, information on continuing education programs, Committee and Chapter reports, plus clinical articles and book reviews.
  - The Clinician Vol. 40 No. 2, 2009 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 41 No. 1, 2010 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 41 No. 2, 2010 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 42 No. 1, 2011 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 42 No. 2, 2011 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 43 No. 1, 2012 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 43 No. 2, 2012 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 44 No. 1, 2013 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 44 No. 2, 2013 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 45 No. 1, 2014 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 45 No. 2, 2014 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 46 No. 1, 2015 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 46 No. 2, 2015 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 47 No. 1, 2016 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 47 No. 2, 2016 Fall
  - The Clinician Vol. 48 No. 1, 2017 Spring
  - The Clinician Vol. 48 No. 2, 2017 Fall
- Subject Files, 1977-2017; Undated; 4; 1 cubic ft.
  This series contains programs and fliers from events organized by the NYSSCSW and various local chapters, plus materials on the society's professional assistance to its members regarding the treatment of patients under managed care.
  - Professional Standards Review Organization, 1977; 1979; 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NYSSCSWP Westchester Chapter Annual Fall Institute, 1983 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Party Push, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Vendorship Committee, 1984-1985; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles About Hillel Bodek, 1984-1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Continuing Education Annual Conference, 1986 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Continuing Education Program, 1987 Spring (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Open House, 1988 April (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - NYSSCSWP Nassau Chapter 9th Annual Membership Meeting, 1988 September (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Workshop Schedule, 1988 September-1988 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Education Committee Conference, 1988 October (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NYSSCSWP Staten Island Chapter Meetings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Meeting, 1989 March (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NYSSCSWP Westchester Chapter Conference, 1989 April (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Meeting, 1990 October (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Managed Care, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NYSSCSWP Annual Conference, 1991 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Managed Care, 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Managed Care, 1992; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Managed Care and Federal Legislation, 1992; 1996-1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Education Committee Conference, 1993 February (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Managed Care, 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Coalition of Mental Health Professional and Consumers, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Managed Care, 1994; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Managed Care Stories, 1994-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Managed Care, 1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Managed Care, 1996 January-1996 April (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Managed Care, 1996 May-1996 December (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - NYSSCSW Nassau Chapter Conference, 1996 October (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Managed Care, 1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Loneliness, Isolation, and Disillusionment" Conference, 1998 November (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Managed Care, 1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Managed Care, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Master's in Social Work Curriculum, 2003 March; Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - NYSSCSW 34th Annual Conference, 2003 May (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - NYSSCSW Annual Membership Meeting, 2004 January (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - NYSSCSW 35th Annual Conference, 2004 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Managed Care, 2004; 2007 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - NYSSCSW Met Chapter First Annual Meeting, 2005 November (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - NYSSCSW Annual Membership Meeting, 2006 January (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - NYSSCSW 37th Annual Conference, 2006 May (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - NYSSCSW Annual Membership Meeting, 2007 January (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - NYSSCSW Vendorship Conference, 2007 March (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - NYSSCSW 38th Annual Conference, 2007 May (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - NYSSCSW Annual Membership Meeting, 2008 January (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - NYSSCSW Met Chapter Conference, 2011 March (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - NYSSCSW 43rd Annual Conference, 2012 May (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - NYSSCSW 43rd Annual Membership Meeting, 2012 October (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - NYSSCSW 44th Annual Education Conference, 2013 May (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Marsha Wineburgh Agenda, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Managed Care, 2015-2017; Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letter From Rockland Chapter President, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - NYSSCSW Annual Membership Meeting, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - NYSSCSWP Metropolitan Chapter Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - NYSSCSWP Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - NYSSCSWP Queens Chapter Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - NYSSCSWP Westchester Chapter Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Partial List of NYSSCSW Education Conferences, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)